<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The door of truth opened: or, A brief and true narrative of the occasion how Mr Henry Burton came to shut himself out of the church-doors of Aldermanbury: published in answer to a paper, called, Truth shut out of doors: for the vindication of the minister and people of Aldermanbury, who are in this paper most wrongfully and unjustly charged; and also for the undeceiving of the underwriters, and of all those that are misinformed about this businesse. In the name, and with the consent of the whole church of Aldermanburie.</title>
            <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E311_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200459</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861200</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861200</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 51:E311[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The door of truth opened: or, A brief and true narrative of the occasion how Mr Henry Burton came to shut himself out of the church-doors of Aldermanbury: published in answer to a paper, called, Truth shut out of doors: for the vindication of the minister and people of Aldermanbury, who are in this paper most wrongfully and unjustly charged; and also for the undeceiving of the underwriters, and of all those that are misinformed about this businesse. In the name, and with the consent of the whole church of Aldermanburie.</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith at the Crane in Pauls-Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edmund Calamy by Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Burton, Henry. Truth shut out of doores (Wing B6173).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burton, Henry, 1578-1648. --  Truth shut out of doores.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113328:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DOOR OF TRVTH OPENED: OR, A brief and true Narrative of the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion how M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Burton</hi> came to ſhut himſelf out of the <hi>Church-doors</hi> of <hi>Aldermanbury:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed in Anſwer to a Paper, called, TRVTH SHVT OVT OF DOORS:</p>
            <p>For the Vindication of the Miniſter and People of <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> who are in this paper moſt wrongfully and unjuſtly charged; and alſo for the undeceiving of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderwriters,</hi> and of all thoſe that are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informed about this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>In the Name, and with the conſent of the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Aldermanburie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 16.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now I beſeech you, brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 11.16.</hi>
                  </bibl> But if any man ſeem to be contentions, we have no ſuch cuſtome, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Churches of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 1.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now I beſeech you, brethren, by the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that all speak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions among you, but that ye be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-yard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113328:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113328:2"/>
            <head>THE Door of Truth opened.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed M. <hi>Burton</hi> in the later end of his Paper, to call his <hi>Narrative</hi> an <hi>unpleaſing diſcourſe.</hi> A fit <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thete</hi> for ſuch a paper. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>npleaſing</hi> we believe to <hi>God</hi> himſelf; <hi>unpleaſing</hi> to all meek, humble and peaceable Chriſtians; <hi>unpleaſing</hi> to his <hi>quondam</hi> loving neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and friends of <hi>Aldermanbury; unpleaſing</hi> to moſt of the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwriters;</hi> and we conceive it will at laſt become an <hi>unpleaſing</hi> diſcourſe to M. <hi>Burton</hi> himſelf, when the judicious and impartiall Reader ſhall clearly and fully underſtand the true grounds and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his diſcontinuing to preach his <hi>Catechiſticall Lecture</hi> in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermanbury;</hi> which before we come to declare, we deſire the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to take notice of the Title of the <hi>Narrative,</hi> which is, <hi>Truth ſhut out of doors:</hi> or, <hi>A brief and true Narrative of the occaſion and manner of proceeding of ſome of Aldermanbury Pariſh, in ſhutting their Church-doors against me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Title M. <hi>Burton</hi> doth ſeem to aſſume to himſelf the name of <hi>Truth</hi> (which is a very high and ſacred <hi>Title</hi>) and to make the <hi>ſhutting</hi> of <hi>him</hi> out of doors, to be the <hi>ſhutting</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> out of doors: which how fit it is for any humble and ſelf-denying Miniſter to ſpeak of himſelf, we leave it to the Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>And beſides, This Title layeth a very heavie charge upon the <hi>Church-wardens</hi> and others of <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> as if they were now become enemies to the truth, as if they had ſhut the Church-doors upon truth, inſomuch as that it is cried up and down the ſtreets of the City, <hi>Truth ſhut out of the doors of Aldermanbury,</hi> to the great diſparagement and defamation of us all; ſo great, as that we conceive it to be a high breach of the ninth Commandment, and we expect <hi>Reparation.</hi> And as he <hi>hopes in this his Narative that</hi> M. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy will finde juſt cauſe publikely to confeſſe</hi> at his next <hi>day of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113328:3"/>Let us be aſhamed and confounded,</hi> ſo he muſt give us leave to ſay, that we expect, and that more juſtly the like from him.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, if the Reader will be pleaſed to conſider the <hi>Texts</hi> of Scripture that are ſubjoyned to the Title page. In which he doth ſecretly ſeem to inſinuate (for to what purpoſe elſe are they there put?) That becauſe he is not ſuffered to preach any longer at <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manbury</hi> (upon juſt cauſes hereafter to be mentioned) That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Truth is fallen in the ſtreets, and equity cannot enter.</hi> That therefore, <hi>We are a rebellious people, lying children, that will not hear the Word of the Lord, who ſay to the Prophets, Propheſie not right things.</hi> And like to <hi>the Scribes and Phariſees, who commanded Peter, Iames and Iohn not to teach in the Name of Chriſt.</hi> Now whether this be not a perverting of Scripture, and an unparallel'd affront to <hi>Alderman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> we leave it unto the unbiaſſed Reader to determine. In the laſt text he juſtifieth himſelf, in the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 20.27. which puts us in minde of a <hi>Book</hi> written by him of his life and ſufferings, wherein he is pleaſed to compare his ſufferings with the ſufferings of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and in many things to preferre his ſufferings above <hi>Pauls</hi> ſufferings. And yet we doe not write this, as if we would any waies undervalue M. <hi>Burtons</hi> great ſufferings, for which we <hi>bleſſe God,</hi> and for which we ſhall alwaies honour him, and we doe believe that therein he did great ſervice to the Churches of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. But howſoever we would deſire him to remember what
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 11. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith of many <hi>Confeſſours</hi> (eſpecially of one <hi>Lucianus</hi>) that had endured much for Chriſts cauſe in times of perſecution, and yet afterwards in times of peace, preſuming upon their former ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, did venture to do many things which did much tend to the great diſturbance of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">And what he writeth to <hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imus</hi> and <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> &amp; other <hi>Confeſſours,</hi> that after their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſufferings for Chriſt, made a <hi>ſchiſme</hi> in the Church, &amp; fell away to the <hi>Novation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> Cypr. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 44. And what <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> ſaith of one <hi>Natalius,</hi> that had endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red much for the truth, &amp; yet afterwards fell into a grievous errour, till God was pleaſed by his <hi>Argels</hi> to whip him into the truth again Euſeb. <hi>l</hi> 5 <hi>cult.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving the <hi>Title</hi> page, let us come to the <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>In which there are divers things <hi>ſuppoſed,</hi> and taken for <hi>granted,</hi> which are not to be ſuppoſed; and many things <hi>miſreported</hi> and <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented.</hi> And therefore that the <hi>Reader</hi> may have the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſet before them in the right colours, we are neceſſitated to ſhew what thoſe falſe <hi>ſuppoſitions</hi> and falſe <hi>repreſentations</hi> are. And M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> muſt not be offended with us for ſpeaking the truth. We profeſſe that we write theſe things with grief of heart. For we know that the <hi>common enemy</hi> will take advantage by our differences; but woe be to him by whom thoſe offences come. For our parts we declare
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113328:3"/>to all the world, that had it not been that <hi>Truth</hi> would have been quite <hi>ſhut out of doors</hi> by our ſilence, we would not have anſwered this <hi>Narrative</hi> of <hi>Truth ſhut out of doors.</hi> But to come to the matter it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, It is taken for granted thorowout the whole <hi>Narrative,</hi> That the ſhutting of <hi>Independency</hi> out of doors, is the <hi>ſhutting of truth out of doors.</hi> And that the deſiring of M. <hi>Burton</hi> to forbear to preach his <hi>Congregationall way,</hi> is to deſire him to <hi>refrain</hi> from preaching <hi>the truth of God.</hi> And that if M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſhould balk this controverſie, he ſhould <hi>balk a neceſſary truth of God,</hi> and ſhould <hi>ſhut up truth cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.</hi> And many ſuch like expreſſions, which will not we hope any whit move a wiſe and judicious <hi>Reader.</hi> For an opinion is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>truth,</hi> becauſe M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaith it is. Bold and <hi>confident aſſertions</hi> may work upon thoſe that have mens perſons in admiration: but a wiſe and underſtanding <hi>Chriſtian</hi> will conſider not ſo much who ſpeaks, nor the confidence of him that ſpeaks, as the weight and ſtrength of the arguments upon which his confidence is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. There was an <hi>Athenian</hi> that laid confident claim to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſhip that came to the haven, and yet he had no true right to any, and was accounted a mad man for his labour. The reformed <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> know no ſuch <hi>truths of God.</hi> An he himſelf (we believe) hath not been many years of this judgement. But howſoever let not M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> aſſume ſuch a high meaſure of confidence to himſelf, as to make his judgement, and the <hi>truths of God</hi> to be <hi>terms convertible.</hi> The world is too wiſe to believe any ſuch thing. And many will ſay that this is <hi>ſelf worſhip</hi> and <hi>ſelf-idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, M. <hi>Burton</hi> doth take it for granted, <hi>That he is bound to preach every truth of God that comes in his way,</hi> in this his Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Lecture; and <hi>that he is not to ſhut up any truth cloſe priſoner</hi> (as his phraſe is) <hi>And he bleſſeth God that the Committee when they met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not one of them did uſe a word of perſwaſion to him to balk any one truth in opening and plowing up the Scriptures.</hi> But we are informed by ſome of the Committee, that upon his firſt admiſſion to this Lecture, he was deſired not to meddle with the points in controverſie (which he is pleaſed to call the <hi>truths of God</hi>) And that he did promiſe ſo to do, or at leaſt by his ſilence gave his conſent. And we can upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> certain grounds aſſure the <hi>Reader,</hi> that M. <hi>Burtons</hi> medling with the points in difference is much diſpleaſing to moſt of them, who profeſſe that they will not countenance him, nor maintain him in it. And that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113328:4"/>they ſent one of their Committee to M. <hi>Burton,</hi> ſince his ſaid Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture ceaſed, to perſwade him to deſiſt from preaching his Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent opinions amongſt us. And therefore we wonder that M. <hi>Burton</hi> durſt write after ſuch a manner concerning the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee. Howſoever, if M. <hi>Burton</hi> will yet perſevere in this his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this be alſo the judgement of his brethren (as we hope it is not) mark the miſchiefs that muſt neceſſarily follow hereupon.</p>
            <p n="1">1 All underwriters, that are not Independents in their judgments, muſt be forced to ſtudy this caſe of conſcience, <hi>Whether they can with a ſafe conſcience contribute to the maintenance of that Lecturer, which is engaged in his conſcience to preach up that opinion which they think diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Word of God, whenſoever it comes in his way?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This miſchief alſo will follow, That all Presbyterian Miniſters, in whoſe Churches theſe our brethren preach, with ſuch a reſolution made known, muſt either by their ſilence be acceſſary to the miſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their people, or by confuting them, make their Pulpits pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſtrife and contention, to the great diſturbance of piety &amp; peace, or do a third thing which will not be very pleaſing to them or us.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems ſtrange to us, that M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſhould thinke himſelf bound to preach his particular opinion in every Congregation: And that all truths (as he cals them) are to be preached at all times, in all places. Is it not ſufficient to preach his private judgement to his own gathered Church, but he muſt think himſelf bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to come to infect (for ſo we judge it) all Congregations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he comes? If this ſhould be the principle likewiſe (which God forbid) of all his brethren, let the wiſe Reader conſider what a City-devouring fire this principle would quickly kindle.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, M. <hi>Burton</hi> doth take it for granted, that he did preach no otherwiſe, <hi>Sept.</hi> 23. 1645. then is ſet down in the <hi>Narrative.</hi> But certainly, if he had preached only, as he ſaith, againſt <hi>man worſhip,</hi> and <hi>will-worſhip, blinde obedience</hi> and <hi>reſting finally</hi> upon mens deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in matters of religion, without looking into the rule of the Word; thoſe of us that heard him, would not have taken the leaſt offence at it: For we have often, and often heard the ſame do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from our own Miniſter. And therefore we think it very raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done of him, to charge M. <hi>Calamy, That he ſhould in the face of God, and of the Congregation, bring this truth as a grievous ſin to be bewailed:</hi> for he cannot but know that this is very unlikely, if not impoſſible to be true.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113328:4"/>
            <p>But there are divers others beſides the Pariſh Clerk (as M. <hi>Burton</hi> by way of ſcorn cals him) that are ready to depoſe, that he did preach otherwiſe then is ſet down in his <hi>Narrative.</hi> And here we cannot but take notice how Biſhop-like he lords it over the poor Pariſh Clerk, telling us of a <hi>garment of many peeces patch'd together.</hi> But ſurely it doth ill become his <hi>gravity</hi> to jeaſt at a mans calling, and worſe become his <hi>goodnes</hi> to trample a poor godly man thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his foot. And let the Reader judge, whether this diſcourſe of the Pariſh Clerk were not ſewed into the Narrative, as an old patch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a new garment, for it comes in very abruptly. But to the buſines. There are thoſe amongſt us, that will depoſe that M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaid, <hi>That for a people to wait upon man for a form to worſhip God by, was Idolatry.</hi> Nay, <hi>For a people to wait upon Parliament or Aſſembly, for a form to worſhip God by, was worſe then corporall Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But, ſaith M. <hi>Burton</hi> in his conference with M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> Will you not give credit to me, as well as to thoſe that informed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If he ſaith, That theſe things are not in his notes, or that he intended not to preach thus, we will believe him. But if M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſaith directly, <hi>He did not preach thus;</hi> We conceive it a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe thing for a man to affirm a <hi>Negative,</hi> when three or four will witneſſe the <hi>Affirmative.</hi> One that heard him at that time, tells, that when he ſaid, <hi>Mistake me not,</hi> he added preſently, <hi>I ſcorn mistakes.</hi> And the party perceived he began a little to be angry. And a man in a paſſion may ſay that which was not in his Notes. But if he thinks this harſh dealing, let him but review his <hi>Narrative,</hi> and conſider how he deals with M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> believing and publiſhing to all the world what he collected out of his Sermon, but from one man, who is one, as we hear, of his own Congregation; whereas we have witneſſe, more then one, for what we ſay. And alſo not believing that M. <hi>Calamy</hi> was not acquainted with his <hi>ſhutting out</hi> (as he cals it) though the <hi>Church-wardens</hi> came on purpoſe to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie him of it. And though he himſelf affirmed it to him: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference he had with him, and though he hath no witneſſe to prove the contrary. So great is his uncharitableneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, It is taken for granted, that M. <hi>Calamy</hi> in his Faſt Sermon, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 24, 1645. did call upon his people to be aſhamed and confounded, as for divers other things, ſo amongſt the reſt for this, <hi>That whileſt the Parliament is ſitting, and labouring to ſettle
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113328:5"/>things, and while the Aſſembly of Ministers are studying to ſettle Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and labouring to heal our breaches, ſhould be ſeparating from us;</hi> Thus much he confeſſeth he ſaid. But now whereas it is added he ſhould ſay,
<note place="margin">And that you may be ſure your Scribe did miſtake M. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamies</hi> Sermon, conſider that one paſſage, though of no great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. M. <hi>Calamie</hi> ſaid, Is not this to croud people <hi>into ſeparated Congregations?</hi> And your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary hath it, <hi>Into ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</hi>
               </note> That this is a ſin to be aſhamed for, <hi>That while a houſe is a purging, men ſhould ſeparate from the defilements, and not waite to ſee what the purging will be.</hi> He conceives this to be either the wilfull, or ignorant miſtake of his <hi>Notary.</hi> And he deſires M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> would name another witneſſe, if he can: For the Apoſtle ſaith, Receive not an accuſation againſt an Elder, under two or three witneſſes. He never thought, much leſſe preached, that we ſhould joyne with a <hi>defiled Church in her defilements.</hi> It is one thing to joyne with a <hi>Church</hi> in her corruptions: Another thing to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from a true Church, becauſe of ſome <hi>defilements</hi> that may be in it. And this is that for which we thinke people ought to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and confounded;</hi> Becauſe for ſome few, (and thoſe but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) defilements they <hi>ſeparate</hi> not onely from <hi>defilements,</hi> but from the true <hi>Churches of Jeſus Christ,</hi> and ingage themſelves into ſeparated Congregations, and doe not waite and tarry to ſee what <hi>Reformation</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> will make. And this is no more then five (as we remember) of your brethren have written, as their judgement in print. And therefore what M. <hi>Burton</hi> writes in his margin, to prove <hi>that every one ought to day, before to morrow, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from preſent defilements,</hi> is but to fight with his own ſhadow. For though we muſt ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>defilements of a Church,</hi> yet we are not to ſeparate from a <hi>Church,</hi> for every <hi>defilement</hi> that is in it. The Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> had many defilements in it, as many we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as the Church of <hi>Alderman-bury;</hi> And ſo had divers of the Churches to which Chriſt wrote. And yet neither Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles doth perſwade the people to ſeparate from thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, becauſe of the defilements. And if this doctrine were true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, we believe men will ſoon finde cauſe to ſeparate from ſome of their Churches,
<note place="margin">A letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by M John Batchelor.</note> as well as ours. The time was when in print, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Alderman-bury</hi> was accounted a <hi>true Church,</hi> even by one of his owne way. And we can aſſure him, That it is much purer now, then it was then.</p>
            <p>But he addes in his Margin. <hi>That each man in his place, and each Miniſter in his place, muſt forthwithfall to a purging out the defilements, not knowing, what others purging may prove to be, and how long we may waite, when in the interim we and our houſe may periſh in our defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113328:5"/>But to this we anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That we would gladly know what theſe <hi>defilements</hi> are, that he ſaith are ſtill in our <hi>Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, How will he prove that theſe <hi>defilements</hi> are of ſuch a <hi>ſoul-deſtroying</hi> nature, that they that live in them, muſt <hi>neceſſarily periſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Doth he not directly tell us in this paſſage, That we muſt not waite to ſee what <hi>Reformation</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> will make? And is not this an unexpreſſible prejudice to their proceedings?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is our opinion, That every Miniſter, and every man ought ſo to adminiſter, and ſo to partake of Gods ordinances, as not to ſin in the adminiſtration, and participation of them. And this they ought to doe to day, before to morrow. But we conceive, and, if it were a fit oportunity, would prove, that this may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>ſeparation</hi> from us. It is one thing to keep our ſelves <hi>pure from pollution,</hi> another thing to gather <hi>Churches out of Churches,</hi> and to ſet up a <hi>new frame of Government,</hi> according to the private judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and people of every particular Church. This we conceive to be his practice, and of dangerous conſequence; and for this we thinke he hath no warrant in the Word, but that he ought to waite yet longer upon the <hi>Magistrates eſtabliſhment.</hi> The Scripture gives much power to Magiſtrates, in purging of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, when corrupted: As we may perceive by the examples of <hi>Aſa, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we are very glad to reade in his Margin, that he makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>ſolemne League and Covenant.</hi> And we hope he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he hath ſworne to indeavour the <hi>extirpation of Hereſy, Schiſme, and profaneneſſe, and to bring the Churches of God, in the three Kingdomes, to the neerest conjunction and uniformity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Burton</hi> goeth on in repeating M. <hi>Calamies</hi> ſermon, according as his one onely witneſſe did dictate unto him. And he ſaith, That he preached that we ſhould likewiſe be aſhamed and confounded, that any ſhould preach, <hi>That it is Idolatry to waite upon the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Aſſembly, and that it is above all corporall Idolatry, to waite upon them till they ſettle a Government.</hi> And here he triumphs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, and inſults, (ſuch is his ſpirit) as much over M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> as he did before over the Pariſh Clerke. He ſaith, <hi>he hopes that</hi> M. Calamy <hi>will in his next ſolemne day of Humiliation, finde juſt cauſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to confeſſe, Let us be aſhamed and confounded.</hi> And in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113328:6"/>part of his Narrative, ſpeaking of the ſame thing, he ſaith, <hi>O that I might heare a ſecond voice in Alderman-bury pulpit, and that on the like ſolemne Faſt day; Let us be aſhamed and confounded, that we have bin aſhamed of the truth, more precious then our lives, and have ſhut it ourt of doors,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But let M. <hi>Burton</hi> tell us, whether he be in jeſt or in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. Doth he think that any meek, or humble Chriſtian, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of this language? For our parts we will not cenſure him, but mourne for him. Doth he not thinke that this is a ſinne to be bewailed, that it ſhould be preached, <hi>That it is worſe then corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Idolatry, to waite upon the Parliament, to ſee what Government they will ſettle?</hi> Is this Doctrine a <hi>Truth more precious then our lives?</hi> Is this doctrine a cleare and undoubted truth? For ſo much he ſeems to ſay in expreſſe termes in his <hi>Narrative,</hi> in theſe words—;<hi>And being at the very worst, a clear and undoubted truth:</hi> which words we cannot but wonder at, and we believe when the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ponders them, he will ſtand amazed at them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaith, That he did not preach as it is here ſet down.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But to this it is anſwered. 1. That now he owns it as it is heere ſet down as a clear and an undoubted truth. 2. That M. <hi>Calamy</hi> did not name him by name. But to this he replieth in his conference with M. <hi>Calamy, That he needed not to name you, for all that heard both you and me, underſtand plainly enough, you did mean me, ſo freſh it is in memory.</hi> But in this anſwer of his he doth ſeem ingenuouſly to confeſſe, that he ſaid the words he denyed he ſaid. For if he ſaid no ſuch thing, and ſpake nothing in derogation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Parliament or Aſſembly, but made honourable mention of both; How is it poſſible that they that heard him, and M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> ſhould ſuppoſe that M. <hi>Calamy</hi> meant him? This very anſwer of his, doth ſeem to confeſſe a guiltineſſe. But to put him out of doubt, it is anſwered. 3. That M. <hi>Calamy</hi> hath good proof of others that have preached to this effect, though he had not. And therefore had juſt cauſe to ſay ſo, although he had not preached at all the day before. It is no wonder to heare men preach up their own practice. No wonder to heare thoſe men preach againſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples tarrying to gather into ſeparated Churches, who daily gather people into ſeparated Churches.</p>
            <p>But he deeply chargeth M. <hi>Calamy</hi> in divers places of his Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113328:6"/>becauſe he did not ſend to him to know the truth of thoſe things, whether he preached them or no, before he ſpake of them in the pulpit.</p>
            <p>But it is anſwered. That if indeed no other had ever preached to the ſame effect, or if he had named M. <hi>Burton</hi> by name, or if he had ſaid it had bin preached in that pulpit the day before, or if it had bin preached in another Church before other people, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there might be ſome ground and reaſon for this accuſation.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing that others have preached the like, and M. <hi>Burton was not named,</hi> and that it was about a ſermon preached in his own <hi>Church,</hi> before ſome of his own people, of whoſe faithfulneſſe he had no reaſon to doubt: And ſeeing it was onely ſpoken in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall way, M. <hi>Burtons</hi> applying of it to himſelf, doth give us juſt cauſe to thinke that he was guilty of it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is taken for granted, that the Church-wardens ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to M. <hi>Burton, That they were ſorry for what they had done, if they had done amiſſe.</hi> But they ſay that they did not ſay, that they were ſorry for the <hi>thing</hi> they had done, but only for ſome <hi>circumſtances</hi> about the manner of doing of it. And they doe now further tell him, that upon diligent ſearch made, they cannot finde out by whoſe authority and allowance he firſt came to preach his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſticall lecture amongſt them. M. <hi>Calamy</hi> ſaith, That none e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake to him, to deſire his conſent. And our former Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens deny, that ever they gave their approbation. <hi>And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſuppoſe, he hath no ſuch cauſe to take it ill, if they upon juſt grounds forbid him to doe that which he never had warrant, nor autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from them to doe at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, And eſpecially M. <hi>Burton</hi> takes it as a thing ſuppoſed, that his ſermon preached <hi>Sept.</hi> 23. 1645. was the <hi>cauſe,</hi> and the <hi>onely cauſe</hi> why he was deſired to forbear preaching at <hi>Alderman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi> Whereas this ſermon was rather an <hi>occaſion</hi> then a <hi>cauſe;</hi> And if a <hi>cauſe,</hi> yet not the <hi>onely</hi> nor <hi>chief cauſe.</hi> The Reader muſt know, that M. <hi>Burton</hi> hath often and often preached his own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate opinion of <hi>Independency,</hi> in his Lecture at <hi>Alderman bury,</hi> to the great offence and ſcandall of ſome of us, that have hereupon reſolved never to heare him more, becauſe we heard ſuch things, which as we thought, were contrary to truth. And therefore M. <hi>Burton</hi> need not wonder <hi>what ſpirit haunted thoſe wals and thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholds, that ſo few people came to heare him in that place.</hi> Surely it was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113328:7"/>the <hi>spirit of errour</hi> that <hi>haunted</hi> them, and drove them away. For ſometimes (as we are informed by thoſe of our own Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that heard him) he would urge <hi>a neceſſity of entring into a Church-way,</hi> and that there <hi>is no expectation of ſalvation without it.</hi> And that it was <hi>as neceſſary to be joyned in Church-fellowſhip, as with Chriſt the head.</hi> Another time, <hi>That a member that walks out of Church-fellowſhip is unuſefull to it ſelf,</hi> as if a foot and a leg be out of joynt, it is unuſeful: for any that walks ſingly and alone, without being in Communion and in a Church-way, <hi>He is out of the body of Chriſt, and ſo is unuſefull to himſelf and others.</hi> Again, <hi>You complain you grow not in grace: but joyn in a Church-way, here is growth in grace. A member out of his proper place growes not.</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, <hi>That none ought to be admitted to the Supper of the Lord, but ſuch as were entred into a Church-way, and had covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a Congregationall-way.</hi> And that <hi>none could receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aright, that had not firſt taken the Church-covenant.</hi> And <hi>that to joyn in a Church-way, is more then to be a Proteſtant at large, becauſe they ought to watch over one another, and thoſe that refuſed to joyn, were as</hi> Cain, <hi>that are ready to ſay,</hi> Am I my brothers keeper? They that wrote his Sermons do alſo tell us, <hi>That he made ſundry Sermons to preſſe the neceſſity of gathering Churches, and covenanting together.</hi> They tell us likewiſe that he ſhewed <hi>how dangerous it was for men to ſet up Churches Provinciall, Nationall, or Parochiall. This was An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian and Babyloniſh, ſet up by the Pope, that all in a Pariſh might come to Maſſe.</hi> Another time he ſpake againſt paying of Tithes, as Popiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such things as theſe he often and often, as occaſion ſerved, did not ſpare to preach and urge with great vehemency: Inſomuch as many of us, and others of the City did reſort to M. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy,</hi> and told him that they wondered how he could with a ſafe conſcience ſuffer ſuch things to be preached, which they knew to be ſo contrary to his judgement. Upon this M. <hi>Calamy</hi> at one time got a reverend <hi>Miniſter</hi> of M. <hi>Burtons</hi> acquaintance to go to him, and to deal mildly with him about theſe things, and to repreſent the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the people. But all the anſwer, as he remembers, returned was, that M. <hi>Burton thought himſelf ingaged to preach the kingdom of Chriſt.</hi> Upon another time M. <hi>Calamy</hi> did likewiſe ſpeak to one of his brethren of that way about it, and all the anſwer to his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt remembrance that he had, was this, M. <hi>Calamy, you know the man, and of what nature he is, it is in vain to speak to him, he will doe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113328:7"/>what he liſt: And it may be he preacheth thus to ſee whether you will cast him out, or no.</hi> At another time M. <hi>Calamy</hi> ſpake with another of the brethren of that way; and his advice was, <hi>To get a meeting of M.</hi> Burton, <hi>and the reſt of his brethren, and they would ſee if they could perſwade him to deſiſt from preaching his Church-way in Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manbury.</hi> But notwithſtanding all this, M. <hi>Burton</hi> continued in his Tueſday Lecture, upon all occaſions promoting his Congregational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, till at laſt, upon occaſion of his Sermon, <hi>Septemb.</hi> 23. 1645. The Church-wardens ſent to him the day before he was to preach, to forbear preaching any more at <hi>Aldermanbury.</hi> And this they did without acquainting M. <hi>Calamy</hi> with it, whatſoever M. <hi>Burton</hi> thinks to the contrary. Of which, as ſoon as M. <hi>Calamy</hi> heard, he ſent for the Church-wardens, and obtained of them upon the <hi>Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> morning (which was the next day after) to go to M. <hi>Burton,</hi> and to declare the whole truth to him, how it ſtood, That M. <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> was a ſtranger to the buſineſſe: That upon M. <hi>Calamies</hi> intreaty they came to him, aſſuring of him that if he would be pleaſed to forbear the points in difference, and to preach <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and him crucified, the doctrines of faith, repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and cheerfully ſuffer him to preach. But he anſwered, as it is ſet down in the Narrative, <hi>That he was not to be reſtrained from preaching any truth of God.</hi> Now let all indifferent Readers judge, whether M. <hi>Burton</hi> by his former practices, and his laſt anſwer doth not <hi>willingly and wilfully ſhut himſelf out of the Church doors of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though he ſuppoſeth his Congregationall-way to be the <hi>truth of God,</hi> yet it is never the more the <hi>truth of God,</hi> becauſe he ſuppoſeth it. And if he thinke it his duty to preach thoſe truths (which we thinke errours) in <hi>Aldermanbury: The ſame conſciences that obligeth him to preach thoſe truths, will oblige M.</hi> Calamy, <hi>who thinks them errours, to preach againſt them.</hi> And by this means the courſe and fruits of his Miniſtery will be much hindered, and the Pulpit made a ſtage of contention, and to ſpeak uncertain ſounds; one thing upon the <hi>Tueſday,</hi> another upon the <hi>Lords day. We ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to M.</hi> Burton, <hi>whether ever he did, or ever will give leave to a Preſbyterian Miniſter to preach his Preſbyterian opinions to his people, that he hath gathered? Or if any ſhould occaſionally preach them to his people, whether he would not thinke himſelf bound in conſcience to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them?</hi> We demand further, <hi>Whether he doth not thinke it his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113328:8"/>to hinder (as farre as he can) that a Preſbyterian Miniſter, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to preach his way (as ſuppoſing it the truth of Chriſt) ſhould be ſuffered to preach once a fortnight to his people. And whether, if he ſhould be a means to hinder it, he can be ſaid to ſhut Truth out of doors?</hi> Let M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſeriouſly ſtudy theſe queſtions, and not thinke it hard meaſure, that he is not ſuffered to doe that in <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> which he would not ſuffer to be done in his own Congregation.</p>
            <p>But further, we would have him to know, that they that are for the <hi>Preſbyterian government,</hi> do firmly believe that that which they hold hath clear light out of the Scriptures, &amp; that they are able to prove it: and that the Congregational-way is an invention of man: and that there is no Word of God for a <hi>Church-covenant: for gathering Churches out of Churches;</hi> for <hi>aſſuming all Church power within themſelves independently:</hi> And that this is a way and means to divide the body of Chriſt into as many ſchiſmes, as there be Congregations. And he muſt not thinke that the <hi>Preſbyterian Miniſters</hi> are ſo void of a good <hi>conſcience,</hi> ſo <hi>cruell</hi> to the <hi>ſouls</hi> of their people, ſo <hi>aſhamed</hi> of the <hi>truths</hi> they hold, as to ſuffer them to be trampled under feet, and their people to be ſeduced by one that ſhall preach in their own Pulpits, with a profeſſion to preach down the Presbyteriall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they in the mean time ſit quiet, and betray the truth, and their people by their wicked ſilence.</p>
            <p>Adde to this what was ſaid before about the Committee, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other things fore-mentioned, and then it will appear to all peaceable and unprejudiced Readers, that there is juſt cauſe that M. <hi>Burton,</hi> continuing in this minde and judgement, ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue his Lecture at <hi>Aldermanbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The ſeventh thing that is miſ-repreſented and miſ-ſtated, is, the conference that was between M. <hi>Burton</hi> and M. <hi>Calamy</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. Of which that there may be a right and full repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Reader muſt know, That when M. <hi>Calamy</hi> perceived by M. <hi>Burtons</hi> anſwer upon the Tueſday, that he was reſolved not to ceaſe preaching the points in difference (and as one very neer him, told ſome of us, that M. <hi>Burton</hi> would not be <hi>muzled up</hi>) he ſadly weighed all things that might happen hereupon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the one ſide</hi> he conſidered, that in this uncharitable age, even good people would be ready to cenſure him very deeply (though never ſo innocent) and charge him as the chief, if not the ſole an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of what was done, and that the times were too too full of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113328:8"/>already, and that there was little need of new rents and ſchiſmes. And therefore he concluded with himſelfe to doe all that he could with a ſafe conſcience for M. <hi>Burtons</hi> re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>On the other ſide,</hi> he conſidered, That this was done without his privity or knowledge, and that the hand of God was in it, and that if now he ſhould be inſtrumentall for his re-admiſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a promiſe, or at leaſt a fair overture upon good ground (for he did not expect a formall promiſe) That M. <hi>Burton</hi> would preach only ſuch things wherein they did both agree, he ſhould for the time to come be acceſſary to all the miſchiefs that might happen, if any of his people ſhould either be led away, or if not quite led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, yet puzled and enſnared by what M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſhould preach. And this his ſcruple was the more encreaſed, becauſe M. <hi>Burton</hi> had already taken one of his Congregation into his Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever acquainting him with it (which is ſurely a great injury to M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> and ſo great, as that we have good cauſe to beleeve, that few of his brethren would have done the like.) By this he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that M. <hi>Burton</hi> was reſolved to catch (we will not ſay, to ſteal) as many as he could from his Church. Now here was the <hi>caſe of conſcience, How far he might be active in M.</hi> Burtons <hi>re-admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> He conſulted with godly, learned. He was told, <hi>That as things then ſtood, he could not with a ſafe conſcience intreat for his re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, unleſſe he had ſome ground to believe that M.</hi> Burton <hi>would not preach his Congregationall-way amongſt his people.</hi> Upon this the Wedneſday after this Tueſday, M. <hi>Francis Shute</hi> comming to viſit M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> who was ſick, M. <hi>Calamy</hi> communicated the whole buſineſſe to him, and deſired him to relate it to the Committee, that they might have a right underſtanding of it, and to endeavour that the Committee might uſe their intereſt in M. <hi>Burton</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him to forbear the points in difference, that ſo he might bere admitted. How farre M. <hi>Francis Shute</hi> did manifeſt his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of M. <hi>Burtons</hi> medling with his Congregationall way in his preaching at Aldermanbury, we will not relate. But as M. <hi>Calamy</hi> conceives, upon M. <hi>Shutes</hi> applying himſelf to the Committee, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the conference ſpoken of in the Narrative. For M. <hi>Shute</hi> came afterwards and told him that M. <hi>Burton</hi> would come to him. But he replied, That as ſoon as he was well he would go to M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> But M. <hi>Burton</hi> prevented him.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:113328:9"/>
            <p>Little did M. <hi>Calamy</hi> think that ſuch a private conference ſhould have been made publike, and cryed up and down the City, and therefore he had no witneſſe on his ſide to atteſt what he ſaid. But ſeeing it is the will of God to have it ſo, and to ſuffer the fire of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to kindle more and more, let the pious and peaceable Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er read over the conference, and then tell us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether moſt of the conference be not already anſwered: Whether it doth not miſ-repreſent the whole buſineſſe, and take the ſix things before named for granted, which we have abundantly proved to be far otherwiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether in this conference M. <hi>Burton</hi> doth not diſcover an <hi>Epiſcopall ſpirit,</hi> rather then M. <hi>Calamy.</hi> Indeed M. <hi>Calamy</hi> did not enumerate the particular things, for which we took offence at ſome of M. <hi>Burtons</hi> Sermons: but the reaſon was, becauſe he was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to <hi>accommodate</hi> and <hi>reconcile</hi> differences, and not to increaſe them. And this was the reaſon likewiſe, why his Clerk was not ſent for, becauſe, as M. <hi>Francis Shute</hi> then ſaid, it would but increaſe the conteſt between M. <hi>Burton</hi> and him, and make the breach wider.</p>
            <p>Adde further, That M. <hi>Calamy</hi> thinks that M. <hi>Burton</hi> hath miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed many of his Queſtions, putting one before another, to the great prejudice of the conference, and interlaced many things, which (as he remembers) M. <hi>Burton</hi> did not ſay at the conference, and hath left out many things that M. <hi>Calamy</hi> did ſay.</p>
            <p>One thing M. <hi>Calamy</hi> chargeth him withall, of which we will give the Reader a fuller account. M. <hi>Calamy</hi> had preached many Sermons out of <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6. concerning brotherly reproof, and the duty of <hi>watching over one another,</hi> and had ſhewed that this duty did belong to a Chriſtian, as a Chriſtian; not only as he was a <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a Church;</hi> and had likewiſe ſhewed how farre they that were members of the ſame Church, were to <hi>watch over one another.</hi> Hereupon he came to juſtifie an equall and prudent diviſion and bounding of Congregations by Pariſhes, that ſo by their neer living together, they might the better watch over one another. And then he came to anſwer that Queſtion, <hi>Whether the living in the ſame Pariſh did make a man a member of that Church to which his houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs?</hi> It would be too long to repeat what was anſwered. But the next Tueſday M. <hi>Burton</hi> preached directly againſt bounding of Congregations by Pariſhes, ſaying, it was <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Antichristian,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113328:9"/>or to that effect, as thoſe that heard him relate. Vpon this M. <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> when he came again to preach of this ſubject, amongſt other things wiſhed that all controverſies amongſt brethren might be laid aſide, and that we would agree to preach Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Then comes M. <hi>Burton,</hi> and calleth upon all Miniſters to ſet up <hi>Chriſts Kingdome,</hi> and addes, But ſome will ſay, we muſt not meddle with theſe things, but onely <hi>preach faith and repentance.</hi> He anſwered, <hi>we must not leave out faith and repentance, but we must preach Chriſts Kingdome, for we have liberty now to ſpeak,</hi> &amp;c. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to this ſtory, M. <hi>Calamy</hi> not naming the ſtory, charged M. <hi>Burton</hi> for preaching point blanke againſt him. And his anſwer is, <hi>It is poſſible I might caſually doe ſo, yet without reference to you.</hi> Whether this anſwer be ſatisfactory, let the Reader judge. We are ſure that if it be ſufficient, it will quit M. <hi>Calamy</hi> of moſt of the accuſations that are brought againſt him in the Narrative.</p>
            <p>As for that concerning M. <hi>Lockier,</hi> we ſpake ſince with the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour</hi> of the place where he Lectures, and he aſſures us, that it is true that M. <hi>Lockier</hi> hath ingaged himſelf by promiſe, not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the point in difference between the Independents and Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>And for M. <hi>Francis Shute,</hi> becauſe we love and honour him, we will forbear to write what we know. M. <hi>Calamy</hi> remembers not that M. <hi>Hartford</hi> ſhould ſay. The Committee thought very hard that theſe things ſhould be ſo carried, before M. <hi>Calamy</hi> had firſt ſpoken with M. <hi>Burton.</hi> The Committee ſurely are wiſer, then to condemne a man before he be heard. We believe the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee will not own this ſpeech, much leſſe thanke him for it.</p>
            <p>Whereas in the later end of the conference M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he was ſent home, without any hope of having the doors unlocked, we leaving him without hope of our keeping any truth cloſe priſoner.</hi> If theſe words were well weighed, they would give a <hi>key</hi> to the <hi>Reader</hi> to unlock the whole buſineſſe. M. <hi>Burton</hi> reſolveth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he preacheth, to let all truths out of priſon, and whoſoever will open the doors of their Church to him, muſt open their doors to all his Independent opinions alſo. How farre the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee and the reſt of the Vnderwriters, and others whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes will approve of this, we know not. But ſure we are, that whoſoever readeth the <hi>conference,</hi> and this anſwer to it, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that M. <hi>Burtons</hi> high language againſt M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> doth ſavour
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113328:10"/>more of ſelf-conceitedneſſe then of juſt accuſation.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The eighth particular which is miſ-related in this Narrative, is about a ſecond conference, which, as M. <hi>Burton</hi> ſaith, he procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of love to Aldermanbury, <hi>There were two of the Committee ſent to M.</hi> Calamy, <hi>to know of him, whether he would be pleaſed to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to exerciſe there ſtill: His finall anſwer to them,</hi> was; <hi>That he could not in conſcience ſuffer me any longer to preach there, becauſe his people were of a contrary judgment.</hi> Thus farre M. <hi>Burton.</hi> Now that the Reader may underſtand how farre this Relation is from truth, we will ſet down M. <hi>Calamies</hi> anſwer, as it was written, word for word, by one of thoſe two, who were ſent to him, and it is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> the firſt, 1645. M. <hi>Iames Storey,</hi> and M. <hi>Robert Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> were ſent by the Committee to M. <hi>Calamy,</hi> about M. <hi>Burtons</hi> preaching in that Church. And his anſwer was,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That he had no hand, directly or indirectly, in keeping of him out, and that that buſineſſe lay in the Church-wardens and Pariſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That if the Committee will ſend under their hands, that they are confident upon good grounds that M.</hi> Burton <hi>will preach the truths of Chriſt, and not meddle with the controverſie, he will be a means to the Church-wardens, and the Pariſhioners for his re-admiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this anſwer it may appear to all the world how deſirous M. <hi>Calamy</hi> is that M. <hi>Burton</hi> may be reſtored to his Lecture amongſt us. And we can further evidence to all that are willing to receive ſatisfaction, that M. <hi>Calamy</hi> hath dealt with many of the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, and hath made uſe of one of them in eſpeciall manner to deal with M. <hi>Burton,</hi> to ſee whether he could obtain of him to joyn with M. <hi>Calamy</hi> in a way of peace and unity. But M. <hi>Burton</hi> will either preach all his minde at his Church, or not preach at all. Now whether M <hi>Burton,</hi> or M. <hi>Calamy</hi> be in the fault, let the world judge. And that all men may likewiſe be fully convinced of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermanburies</hi> love, and good affections towards M. <hi>Burton,</hi> we doe here profeſſe to all that read theſe lines, That if M. <hi>Burton</hi> will be pleaſed to forbear preaching his Congregationall way amongſt us, and preach ſuch things, wherein both ſides agree, we will re-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him with all readineſſe and cheerfulneſſe, and will promiſe to endeavour upon all occaſions to come and hear him. Which offer, if <hi>M. Burton</hi> refuſeth, let the world judge, whether <hi>M. Burton</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:113328:10"/>ſhuts himſelf, or be ſhut out of the Church-doores of <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we have given an Anſwer to this <hi>unpleaſing Narrative,</hi> ſo farre as it concerns us. And it may be the anſwer will be as <hi>unpleaſing</hi> as the Narrative. But our Apology is, <hi>That ours is forc'd, his is voluntary.</hi> It is a ſad thing that <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> that hath had ſo much truth preached unto it, and hath had ſo many famous Preachers of truth, ſhould now be cried up and down the ſtreets of the City, as a people that ſhut <hi>Truth out of Doors.</hi> Who would not riſe up to wipe off ſuch an aſperſion? <hi>Truth it is the purchaſe of the blood of Ieſus Chriſt: It is that which Chriſt brought into the world with him: For grace and truth comes by Ieſus Chriſt. Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to bear witneſſe of the Truth. Truth it is the light and life of the ſoul, the Spouſe of the underſtanding, the food and ſuſtenance of the ſoul: It is to be preferred before gold and ſilver; pearls and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones are but dung and droſſe in compariſon of it.</hi> And therefore if we contend earneſtly for the truth, and make it appear to all men, that we are farre from ſhutting <hi>Truth out of Doors.</hi> We hope that all that are moderate and ſober Chriſtians will not only not accuſe us, but commend us for it. We have done. <hi>The Lord open all the doors of our hearts, that we may receive peace and truth as unſeparable gueſts to lodge within us for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THere is one thing that M. <hi>Burton</hi> mentioneth in the <hi>Narrative,</hi> which though it concerns not <hi>Aldermanbury,</hi> yet we muſt not wholly bury it in ſilence, and that is concerning the <hi>late large Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for the ſpeedy eſtabliſhment of Religion.</hi> Of which he ſpeaks ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſhonourably, as alſo of the Petitioners, as of men led with blinde obedience, and pinning their ſouls upon the <hi>Prieſts ſleeve.</hi> We leave it to the Petitioners to anſwer for themſelves. For our parts we conceive that no Reader, unleſſe blinded with prejudice, can charge them with blinde obedience. For the Petitioners doe not deſire to have the <hi>Modell</hi> of the reverend Aſſembly eſtabliſhed, but the government of Chriſt eſtabliſhed, A Modell whereof, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113328:11"/>words, <hi>A Modell whereof,</hi> &amp;c. come in with a parentheſis, and the ſentence is compleat without them. All that they affirm about the Modell is, That the <hi>Reverend Aſſembly</hi> hath framed a Modell of the government of Chriſt, according to their ability, and preſented it to the Parliament. And who but he that hath pinned his faith upon an Independents ſleeve, can except againſt this? But if M. <hi>Burton</hi> be diſpleaſed with the Modell of the Reverend Aſſembly, we would intreat him that he at laſt, after ſo long expectation, would ſet forth his <hi>Modell.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
